<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hidden things made manifest by the light in a plain distinction between condemnation and temptation : wherein is shewed how the rightetous law of God is ministered upon the transgressor, and how it is to be by all received and continued under, through it, as a schoolmaster to come to Christ, by him to have the sin done away forever : also of temptation, what it is, and how it may be known and discerned from condemnation, that out of temptation man may be delivered and kept with the light of Christ, who was tempted and did overcome : with a direction to them who profess the knowledge of the truth, and live not in the power of God, that they may know the entrance within the vail, where the temptations are overcome, and where the foolish virgins cannot enter / given forth for such who say they see, and yet their sin remaineth ... by a member of the church and body of Christ ... Humphrey Smith.</title>
            <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13777495</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13777495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hidden things made manifest by the light in a plain distinction between condemnation and temptation : wherein is shewed how the rightetous law of God is ministered upon the transgressor, and how it is to be by all received and continued under, through it, as a schoolmaster to come to Christ, by him to have the sin done away forever : also of temptation, what it is, and how it may be known and discerned from condemnation, that out of temptation man may be delivered and kept with the light of Christ, who was tempted and did overcome : with a direction to them who profess the knowledge of the truth, and live not in the power of God, that they may know the entrance within the vail, where the temptations are overcome, and where the foolish virgins cannot enter / given forth for such who say they see, and yet their sin remaineth ... by a member of the church and body of Christ ... Humphrey Smith.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Temptation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101766:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> HIDDEN THINGS Made manifeſt by the LIGHT;</p>
            <p>In a plain Diſtinction between <hi>CONDEMNATION</hi> and <hi>TEMPTATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed how the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous LAW of God is miniſtred upon the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, and how it is to be by all received and continued under, through it, as a Schoolmaſter to come to Chriſt, by him to have the ſin done away for ever.</p>
            <p>Alſo of Temptation, what it is, and how it may be known and diſcerned from Condemnation, that out of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation Man may be delivered and kept with the Light of Chriſt, who was tempted and did overcome.</p>
            <p>With a direction to them who profeſs the knowledge of the truth, and live not in the power of God, that they may know the entrance within the Vail, where the Temptations are overcome, and where the fooliſh Virgins cannot enter.</p>
            <p>Given forth for ſuch who ſay they ſee, and yet their ſin remaineth; and may be ſerviceable to ſuch who can hear and underſtand the things of God, that thoſe who are yet blinde may no longer put darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe, as it is written,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have ears: Let all the Nations be gathered together, and let the people be aſſembled; who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them can declare this, and ſhew his former things? Let them bring forth their witneſs that they may be juſtified, or let them hear and ſay it is truth, Iſa.</hi> 43. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>By a member of the Church and body of Chriſt, for whoſe ſake I ſuffer bonds in the Common Goal and Houſe of Correction at <hi>VVincheſter,</hi> where my <hi>Name</hi> is written, <hi>Humphrey Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the Bull and Mouth neer <hi>Alderſgate</hi> 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101766:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101766:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Hidden things made manifeſt by the Light in a plain diſtinction between <hi>Condemnation</hi> &amp; <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Miniſtration of Condemnation.</head>
               <p>THE World being ſet in mans heart, and ſin being in the world before the promiſe was made, which promiſe was before the Law, by which the ſin is diſcovered; which ſin was in the world before the promiſe, yet the promiſe was before the Law; and yet until the Law come, death reigns over that to which the promiſe is, and ſinne ſeparateth man from God, the which is not clearly ſeen until the Commandment (which is Light) is come, the miniſtration whereof is condemnation unto MAN, being found in the tranſgreſſion; the which Miniſtration of Condemnation is to <hi>paſs over all,</hi> having ſinned; and when this commeth, it finds man in the death, and by it is ſinne revived, whereby man comes to ſee a body of ſin, which ſtands between him and God, ſo that he is afraid of the dreadful power of God, miniſtred forth through the law, to ſlay him that hath tranſgreſſed, the which ſome coming to ſee, or in the leaſt meaſure to feel, calleth it a temptation becauſe it maketh him ſenſible that condemnation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to him, and that all his profeſſion and building upon the promiſe in that which the promiſe was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and ſeeing that if he lyeth down to receive this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that then all his profeſſion and knowledge, zeal, wiſdom and prayers, (which did ariſe out of that ground which was curſed by reaſon of the ſinne that was in the world before either the promiſe, the profeſſion, or the law) will be all ript up from him as filthy Rags, and that his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101766:3"/> ſhame and nakedneſs muſt appear, as it's written, <hi>Every mouth ſhall be ſtopped, and every one ſhall ſtand guilty before God, and no darkneſs nor ſhadow of death ſhall hide the workers of iniquity from the mighty hand of God, who bring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the hidden things of darkneſs, and rips open the ſecret of the heart, ſo that the moſt ſecret ſins that ever was committed are clearly made manifeſt, and juſtly charged upon the head of the tranſgreſſor, who stands in enmity to God, who will wound the head of the tranſgreſſor, and plead in righteouſneſs with him in whom the ſin is found, though not made manifeſt until the time that the Law is come by which it is diſcovered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this Miniſtration of Condemnation is not a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, though many call it ſo, who being blind, put dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for light, and light for darkneſs; for that which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth man his ſin, doth not tempt man to ſin, but rather brings man in fear that he may not ſin; for becauſe of ſin was the Law added; and the Law was given after much of the love, preſervation, power, deliverances, and the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Lord had been ſeen, and it was given in the Wilderneſs where ſometime there was want of bread and water, where was Serpents, Scorpions and many trials; where the figure of him who was to heal the wounded, and take away the ſting of death, and ſave the life of man, was lifted up on high without them; the which figure or outward bodily appearance, was prepared by <hi>Moſes:</hi> And Chriſt had a body prepared him, both w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the carnal eye might ſee, &amp; the carnal mind contend about, (even as the Devil about the body of <hi>Moſes)</hi> but the ſubſtance of the figure, Chriſt the Light, Gods power, being not received within, in the heart, and ſo ſin (the tranſgreſſion of the Law) remains within, and the figure or that which the natural eye did, or may ſee, was and is looked upon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; and that without doth not take away the ſin within; and theſe knew not the ways of God who ſinned, and at laſt loathed the Manna (calling it light bread) in the Wildernerneſs, even there was the Law miniſtred; they whoſe eyes are open may read and underſtand.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101766:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And where the Law was given forth, there was a Mount, or a high place of the earth, which then trembled by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the dreadful power of the Lord of Hoſts; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath or under the Mount was the Seed and Iſrael of God which was to keep the Law and Life, [Read within and underſtand] and yet by reaſon of that which was hard upon the heart, there was a crying out with dread and horror, and fear, That the Lord might ſpeak no more leaſt they dye; and ſo that which is hard upon the heart, in the which by the Law (which is Light) ſin is found, that is it which is afraid to receive the Law, and come near the darkneſs, and thunders, and tempeſts; and ſo, though many do talk of the Law (being a Schoolmaſter to Chriſt) yet are they as much afraid to receive the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Condemnation, as their Fathers were, who might have boaſted that they were the people of God, and his onely choſen flock, and that the Land of reſt was promiſed to them, and that they had fed upon the paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, (and yet they periſhed before they came to that which was promiſed, who are left for an example) and they might have boaſted and talked much of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and of his wonders, and of his preſence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, and of their own experiences therein, and that therefore they were not to come under the Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Condemnation, and fear, and horror, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and aſtoniſhment; and that they need not now to be afraid of God who had ſhewed them ſo much love and mercy: And many ſuch things might they have pleaded as moſt profeſſing people do now, who can talk of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and deliverances, and of Chriſt and his merits, and Righteouſneſs, and Juſtification, and Redemption, (fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed without them) and eſpecially of Ordinances, and their own experiences of the power of God, but are yet in their ſins, having not received the thing promiſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come to him who is the end of the Law, and maketh an end of ſin, whom many ſatisfie their vain minds with talking of him with the ſame tongue that uſeth deceit; and profeſſing him who is the end of the Law, but the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101766:4"/> Law they deſpiſe, holding the Truth of God in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous grounds, which by the mighty power of God, through the miniſtration of the Law, is to be ſhaken and removed, as it is written, <hi>Sinai alſo was moved, and all Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el trembled, and Moſes did fear and quake,</hi> and once more will the Lord ſhake not onely the Earth, but the heavens alſo, and then ſhall the foundations of the hypocrites be overturned for ever.</p>
               <p>For though the Name of God and Chriſt be profeſſed, yet if <hi>Moſes</hi> Law be deſpiſed, ſuch dye without mercy; for the Law is to remove the iniquity which doth with-hold the mercy and the good things from man; and in the end of the Law is that received by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Law is fulfilled, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is according to the Law &amp; the Prophets; but there is none can come to that in the end of the Law, who refuſe to com to the beginning of the Law, and deſpiſe the Miniſtration of Condemnation, and make a mock at trembling, or at leaſt not knowing what it is, exceedingly to fear &amp; quake, being not in the leaſt ſenſible what that is which muſt be ſhaken and removed before the the thing promiſed be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; for a promiſe may be made long before the thing promiſed be given or obtained; for a promiſe was made unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, and yet it is written of him and many more, that they dyed having not obtained the promiſes; and he that made the promiſe was before the ſin, who miniſtred forth the Law to diſcover the ſinne; through the miniſtration whereof, and by obedience thereunto, that cometh to be received which taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay the ſin, in which all the promiſes are received.</p>
               <p>And ſo all that come to receive the thing promiſed, they receive that which is the end of the Law, and was before the ſin, in which there is no ſin, by which ſin is finiſhed, and him received in whoſe mouth there is found no guile; who bringeth his to be as he is in this preſent world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made the righteouſneſs of God through him, having the righteouſneſs of the Law fulfilled in them, by him who is the end of the Law dwelling in them, in whom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Power worketh mightily, which is more then to talk
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101766:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Law being fulfilled without them; for many ſuch are neither come to that which fulfils the Law, neither yet to the Law it ſelf; and ſuch are hating, reviling, backbiting, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and many ways perſecuting thoſe who witneſſe the Law fulfilled in them, even as <hi>Saul</hi> who was bred up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> and knew that of the Law which was written without, and walked blameleſſe according to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof, and yet knew not that which gave forth the law, but perſecuted him by whom the Law ſhould be fulfilled, Whoſe dreadful power ſmote him down, and a blindneſs came upon that great profeſſor who had profited much in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion above many of his equals: And to that power which ſtruck him blind did he then bow, and became obedient, and afterwards ſaid, <hi>When the commandment came, ſin revived, and I dyed:</hi> And ſo that was ſtruck blinde, and is to be blinded, which profeſſed the Law before it come, and increaſed in that knowledge without the life, and knew not that by which the Law ſhould be fulfilled: Therefore that which ſees, muſt be blind; and that which is blind is to ſee. And this revelation and heavenly viſion he did not then call a Temptation, nor a Deluſion: Neither did he deſpiſe that which ſtruck him blind, and let him ſee a body of ſin, and came to cut him down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſin, but cryed out of his wretchedneſſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted all as droſs and dung; and unto this he was obedient, and this he loved, and did not ſay of it, That it was not able to ſave him from ſinne, the which before did prick for ſinne, though againſt that which prickt he had ſtrived, (which was in him) and it was ſaid unto him, <hi>It is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo that which ſtriveth and kicketh againſt that which pricketh at the heart, is that by which the heart is hardened; for the word is hid in the heart, which word is ſharp as a ſword; which word being preached, ſome were pricked to the heart (others cut to the heart) ſo that many cryed out, <hi>Men and Brethren, What ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> and ſo the word being nigh in which God is ſtriving with man, even piercing the hearts of many, that ſome in ſecret have been ready to cry out and ſay, VVhat ſhall I do to be ſaved? and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101766:5"/> not truly ſenſible what it is in them which did prick and pierce through the heart, and let them ſee themſelves out of Gods Covenant; therefore have they ſtrove againſt it, and called this a Temptation which was the powerful operation of God by the light of his ſon in the heart, calling to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the which they have called a temptation of the Devil (eſteeming it ſo to be) which is moſt horrible blaſphemy and reſiſting of the ſpirit, and refuſing to turn to him that ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: And this is the blindneſs of them who know not God, who by the light of his ſon doth knock at the door of the heart, to miniſter forth the Law, to judge and condemn, and break the hardneſs, that in the broken heart his Word of life might be received, and his power made known, to the confounding of that which kept that in bondage (under the tranſgreſſion) which was given into man before the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion was, out of which tranſgreſſion there is no coming, but by and through the miniſtration of Condemnation, which doth it diſcover in the ground of it, through which there is a coming to receive the Goſpel of Peace, which is the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God not to be preached to the wicked things under which the juſt doth ſuffer, which the Law is to, but by the Lord of glory through the Light, preached to the ſpirit in priſon, that it through the Condemnation of the other, may grow up to lead and guide the creature in all things in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods will from a true ſence of his love in the heart, whereby his whole Law comes to be fulfilled, and the promiſe and the bleſſing received in him who is the end of the Law, who is the light given into man to let him ſee, &amp; to condemn the ſin, the which man being dead in, and in treſpaſſes, doth not love, but is afraid of that which in ſecret judgeth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth him, from the which man flying, forſaketh that by which he ſhould come to receive the mercies of the Lord; but wo to them for ever who ſtrive with their maker, and call him <hi>Belzeebub</hi> who is the light in the heart, and ſhould be Maſter in the houſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore let all take heed of deſpiſing the Law, which is written with the finger of God in the heart whileſt it is yet hard; for the Law of God is perfect, making wiſe the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101766:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the miniſtration thereof is to deſtroy that which did it tranſgreſs, and lead unto him by whom the tranſgreſſion is finiſhed: And this is not a temptation, but a diſpenſation of Gods Juſtice through his righteous Law upon that which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, over which the Law hath power ſo long as that liveth, which the Law is to kill, that through the death of it that might come again to live which was before the Law, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the death, and before the ſin.</p>
               <p>And now when the Law or Miniſtration of Condemnation cometh, man is to ſtand ſtill and wait quietly under it, and not let any thing break through in a haſte, to rage, or gaze, and wonder at that which is ſo dreadful that man is not able to ſtand under it without unſpeakable aſtoniſhment, becauſe of that which then is over him, who then is commanded not to break through leaſt he dye; for the Law is to break through that which cannot keep it, and make way to that which is to keep it, and live for ever; but man is not to break through from under the Condemnation, to that where the Law is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, until that is received by which the Law may be kept; for ſuch who in the condemnation do abide, come at laſt to ſee and receive him that is made under the Law, and is the end of it, and taketh away the ſin; but ſuch who come to the Law, and break out from under the Judgement before the law had brake through, and out down all that in them which could not keep it; ſuch have let in death again to reign over that which with judgment ſhould have been redeemed, to bear away that which the law had power over, and ariſe up with that power, love, life and obedience to God, as in all things to fulfil the whole law of God, which until then, doth ſtill ſtand in force over that and them in which ſin remaineth, which doth tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the law, one tittle whereof ſhall not periſh till all be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, though ſome coming to the law have broke forth, and then healed the wound ſlightly, ſuppoſing it would ſerve their turns to talk of the fulfilling of it by and in another for them, &amp; without them, ſeeing themſelves not able to keep it in all things, not waiting to the end of the law, by it to have all that deſtroyed which could not keep it, and receive that which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not break it; [mark] and in it keep, by it to be lead out of the Wilderneſs of ſin, in the promiſed land to reſt, in it to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101766:6"/> have the dayes prolonged, and the life preſerved; for Chriſt the light cometh to ſave the life.</p>
               <p>And there are many that are now come to peace, domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the land of reſt, who did once come to know the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon <hi>Cains</hi> nature, which then cryed out, That his puniſhment was too heavy to bear, and have alſo come to ſee the beaſt, whoſe head is full of the Names of Blaſphemy, and yet have they not ſtarted aſide like a broken bowe from under the judgement, neither ſuffered the Enemy to prevail over them by temptations, to curſe God and dye, nor to call him <hi>Belzeebub</hi> who is the light which condemns and ſhould be Maſter in the houſe; neither have they deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> law, which is the Miniſtration of Condemnation, and in its time is glorious; but in patience and long-ſuffering under it have wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that without murmuring, or ſuffering that to break forth in rage, which Gods judgements is to; neither have they ſuffered unbelief to prevail over them, but in love to him who was made a curſe, in patience have endured all theſe things, &amp; have been made as free to drink the Cup of Aſtoniſhment, with the dregs thereof, as the Lord was to pour it forth unto them, who now drink the Cup of ſalvation, even the blood of the Lamb which clenſeth from all ſin, whoſe life ſaveth them from the terror of the Pit, who have come to feel the ſeed born and brought forth, though with pangs and ſorrow, which the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is to.</p>
               <p>Thoſe may ſee, hear, and underſtand what I write, who are come to know how the law is handed forth by a Mediator, (who was before the law) and the righteouſneſs of God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt without the law, &amp; ſin diſcovered by the law, and Gods Righteouſneſs revealed by that which was before the law; and that notwithſtanding the law muſt be received, yet by the Works thereof no fleſh ſhall be juſtified, but by obedience of Faith towards God in the blood of his Son, by which all that is done away which tranſgreſt the law; and ſo not of Works, nor of Merits, but of Faith and Love is the Law fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101766:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Concerning Temptation.</head>
               <p>And that thoſe who were born blind, and have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince covered with the blackneſs of darkneſs, through their own Wiſdom, being dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, not feeling nor ſavouring the things of God, but remain in that Religion and Profeſſion which crucified his Son, who is a man of ſorrows, and called him a blaſphemer who is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and ſaid he had a Devil, who came to condemn ſin in the fleſh, whoſe light in every conſcience is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſo long as the evil deeds remain; the which condemnation is not a temptation; for God who is light, tempteth no man to evil. Therefore in love is this writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that no man through blindneſs and ignorance (in his own Wiſdom) may eſteem that to be a temptation which doth condemn, and that out of temptation all ſuch who are tempted may be led and kept by that which doth condemn, vvhich is the pure light of Chriſt vvhich doth iudge and condemn the temptations, and the ſin, and the tranſgreſſor, (who enters into it) and every evil motion which is apt to ariſe in the minde that is darkned and blinded by the god of the World; which mind from the darkneſſe to the light is to be turned, in the light to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve as he hath ſaid, <hi>I am the light, believe in the light;</hi> and it is a temptation which hinders man from believing in the light; and all ſuch keep not the commands of Chriſt, who do not believe and obey the light, and ſuch profeſs his Words, but deny that in which the power of his life doth ſtand.</p>
               <p>And it is a temptation which cauſeth man to deny and refuſe the Law (which is light) and not come under nor receive the Miniſtration of Condemnation, ſuppoſing he is under Grace, and ſo not to come back to the Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath gotten a profeſſion of Chriſt, whoſe day <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſaw, whoſe ſeed came through the Law, of whom Chriſt came who fulfils the Law, and maketh an end of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101766:7"/> ſin, who was in the Church in the Wilderneſs, and in his pitty ſaved them, and bare them all the dayes of old, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the humble feed, that through the Wilderneſs of ſin it might come, and at laſt enioy that by which the ſin is done away for ever.</p>
               <p>And it is a temptation which cauſeth man to call that a temptation which in the conſcience doth ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and let man ſee that he by his ſin is in the fall, the death and the curſe, and that the iudgements of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to him, and that he cannot eſcape the fierce wrath of the Almighty, living in that by which ſin is daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and the righteous Law of God tranſgreſſed, and himſelf out of the Covenant of life, wanting the power of God to bear him up out of iniquity, ſo that he labors and prayes, and cryes ſometimes with tears (like <hi>Eſau)</hi> to keep that alive in the tranſgreſſion, which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to deſtruction; [Conſider this] And ſtrive againſt that which letteth ſee the emptineſs thereof, &amp; condemns afterwards, if a falſe ioy doth not ariſe, ſecretly to glory in what was done, whereby that was ſatisfied and got eaſe which the Judgement was to, which of the Judgement was afraid, and from under it led forth to perform a wil-worſhip from that ground where <hi>Cains</hi> nature bears rule, who can bring a ſacrifice, but the deeds (with the light) ſeen to be evil, who at laſt murthers the Juſt, &amp; the ſin lying at the door, which ſecret ſin cannot be hid from the light in any that commit it, or in whom it is, though never ſo ſecret.</p>
               <p>And it is a temptation which worketh in the dark cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the heart in the time when condemnation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to drive man to diſpair by reaſon of the fierceneſs of the Judgement, and drives him from God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgements, into unbelief and hardneſs of heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; and herein the Tempter prevails over many, ſome whereof then go to deſtroy themſelves, not keeping in patience under the Judgement which was to deſtroy the ſin; for Chriſt the light comes to condemn and deſtroy the ſin, but the life he comes to ſave. Others through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101766:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> have hardned their hearts in ſin, their minds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that in which they cannot believe that ever they ſhall overcome ſin, nor be ſaved from it; and ſuch grow worſe then before, and uſe all means in vain luſtful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to murther that in them which checks, reproves and condemns them for ſin; and many here turn aſide from under the condemnation, many and various ways; ſome who are blind calling it melancholly; ſo that few endure to the end, &amp; enter through the ſtrait Gate by the death, through it the life to find, not waiting with long forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance out of that which haſteth, in patience in the light to ſee, feel and know the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> (brought forth of the barren Womb) which againſt hope, in hope believe: And theſe Temptations leadeth further into ſin, and is not that which condemns for ſin; for that would keep out of ſin, though its Judgements be never ſo heavy upon man for ſin.</p>
               <p>And being that God is known in the ways of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that they who are to receive the promiſe, muſt keep Judgement, and that with Judgement Sions redemption is to be witneſſed; and when Judgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be ſet up in the heart, to iudge, condemn, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, overturn and cut down the head, body and root of all that which by the light is ſeen to be in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, having the form of godlineſs, but not the power which keepeth out of, and free from all ſinne, which the Judgement is to paſs upon: Therefore is that a Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which then draweth forth the mind from under the Judgement, to get eaſe by a ſuppoſed peace with God, from the comprehenſion of ſomething done without, afar off, or long ago, &amp; ſo climbs up another way then by the light within (which I knovv is the door) which condemns &amp; bringeth to Judgement the hidden things of darkneſs, and brings fire and ſword upon the Earth, and ſendeth not peace to it, but ſetteth two at variance within, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by there is much ſtriving in the Womb, and not reſt day nor night becauſe of the War between the two ſeeds, out of which trouble being led, by that which in the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101766:8"/> could not ſtand, ſo that getteth eaſe again, and then man preacheth peace unto himſelf, having got out of ſome trouble, he then ſtriveth more ſtrongly to keep out of it then he did before, and labours much to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a reſting-place to abide in, though that be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with Judgement out of bondage, which thereby ſhould come to obtain reſt and peace for evermore.</p>
               <p>And being that the Law and the Prophets (together) are until <hi>John,</hi> and that the Law is to iudge and cut down that which is above the ſeed exalted; and that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies and openings from the Teſtimony of Witneſs, is to uphold and preſerve under the Judgement, whereby ſome ſecret hopes or refreſhings comes unto that which at laſt out of bondage ſhould be redeemed; therefore it is a temptation which leadeth forth (on that hand) in a Joy, through the reaſon, vvith great ſwelling imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the vain light mind, out of the fear of God, not ſtanding in his counſel, but like the reſt of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, coming to true openings, from it run forth, before that through Judgement be brought forth, which ſhould go before, and lead them in Gods Wiſdom and Counſel to ſtand; and ſuch ſpeak great ſwelling words in a ſecret pride, boaſting of their experiences, but are become the untimely children of the Mother of Harlots, who with their Mother muſt be turned back into the bed of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>And being the Lord God of life hath given his Son a light in the heart, that man might be led, taught and guided by him out of ſin, and giveth power to all them that love, follovv and obey him, to overcome their ſin, vvhoſe light being in Man a free gift from God, and that by no other Name, Way or Means man can ever be ſaved. Therefore it is a Temptation vvhich leadeth out from that in the heart, [Which in it is given there to make an end of ſin] to follovv that vvhich doth not make an end of ſin, nor miniſter povver to them that follovv it, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome their ſin, ſo that they cannot receive that vvhich clenſeth from all ſin; ſuch have the root and ground in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101766:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> them from whence ſinne cometh; but the Root of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> in whom there is no ſin, they are onely profeſſing and talking of without them.</p>
               <p>And it is a Temptation that leadeth man to commit any manner of ſin whatſoever, and keeps man from believing in him that maketh an end of ſin, and keepes man in ſin, and from repentance and turning from ſin, (while that of God in the conſcience is ſtriving with him againſt ſin) perſwading him that he cannot be free from ſin, and to put off the time of true repentance until Gods ſpirit by the light in the heart, hath ceaſed ſtriving; and then ſuch think all is well, becauſe that which judged and condemned them for the leaſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of evil, hath ceaſed ſtriving with them, that ſo they are now quiet, and not judged as formerly for what they do, though they do the ſame things for which formerly they were judged; but let ſuch aſſuredly know, that that which was ſin, is ſin ſtill, though they (inſtead of coming through the Law) are gone back from the Law which did diſcover it, and came to that ſtate again which was before the Law, (or a worſe) where death reigns, and ſin is in the World, though not diſcovered by the Law to them who have deſpiſed the Law, and ſo become dead to that which ſhould fulfil the Law, and alſo dead in that vvhich doth tranſgreſs the Law, even ſo dead in ſin, that not now feeling the weight and burthen thereof, neither yet feeling any thing of God in them, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in them againſt it; and is not their latter end like to be vvorſe then their beginning? And are not ſuch as theſe who have got a profeſſion, more hardened in their ſin, and plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more ſtrongly for their continuance therein, then the Publicans, Harlots, Drunkards and Prophane?</p>
               <p>And it is a temptation which draws forth the mind to fear, love, ſerve, obey, or reſpect any man, or created thing, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, honor, or whatſoever may be named, more then God; or to deny obedience to God for the attaining or retaining thereof, or to let any of the moſt glorious creatures of God fill, and take place in the heart, that in it room may not be found for the power of God to enter; ſo that the life, vertue and ſubſtance of all things in which there is full ſatisfaction, cannot be received.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101766:9"/>
               <p> And it is a temptation that leadeth forth to ſeek, or love the praiſe of men; for if that was out of the Faith which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived honor from men, then that muſt needs be of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil which would compel honor to be given to it; that is it in man of the Devil, vvhich vvould have the begotten of God honor and worſhip it, vvhich vvould take the due honor and praiſe from God, to vvhom alone belongeth all Dominion, Glory, Honor and Obedience, and Praiſes for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>And it is a temptation vvhich draweth forth the minde to Worſhip any other God but he that made all men of one blood, and is above all, and through all, and in you all; Who dwelleth in his people, and what of him may be known, is manifeſt within, Whom all may feel after, and finde, Whom the world by wiſdom doth not know; who abhorreth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of them whoſe hearts are uncircumciſed, and is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed with the peoples words, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2 17. and grieved vvith their iniquity; who heareth not the prayers of men of ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but waiteth to begracious unto ſuch who wait for him in the light of his Son, who was lead as a Lamb dumb, and is of the ſeed of <hi>David,</hi> who was dumb with ſilence, and opened not his mouth while the wicked was in place.</p>
               <p>But when the wicked thing is removed out of his place, &amp; the humble ſeed of the Shepherd raiſed up in his Throne upon his Hill of holineſs, having his Enemies under his feet, then he ſpeaketh with authority, and not as the Scribes.</p>
               <p>Thus man coming into the fear of the Lord, and waiting in the light of his Son in the heart, with it may he ſee and diſcern between that which diſcovereth and condemneth ſin, and that which tempteth to ſin, out of which that man may be redeemed (and kept out of temptations) is this written in love to the ſeed, over which the beaſt, the dog and the ſwine doth vaunt themſelves, who have nothing to do with this, but onely to receive the Cup of aſtoniſhment, which to the Serpents is to be poured forth, who are not to feed upon this which is written.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101766:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A direction in the way to that within the Vail, by which Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are overcome.</head>
               <p>TRuth is that in which the power of God doth ſtand, and in the truth there is no lye; &amp; all them who receive truth from God, in it they receive his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whereby they are made his Sons, in his power toſtand in obedience to his wil, which is that by vvhich they are ſanctified, and by obedience of faith thereunto are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, keeping in ſteadfaſtneſs by the mighty power of God, out of that which doth defile, are preſerved in that Dominion and place of Holineſs into which the Harlots (out of the truth and power) and all proud boaſters (and ſuch who are intruding into things they have not ſeen, and all Murmurers, vvho complain for want of power) doth not enter.</p>
               <p>Therefore all people vvho profeſs the knowledge of the truth, and yet have not received the power of God in which no ſin doth ſtand; Wait ye all in the Light, to know the Vaile rent, and the ground to be removed from whence the Words comes, which darkens that in which the Counſel of God ſhould be received, and wait to feel Judgement and Condemnation upon the Earthly that over the ſeed doth rule; and keep Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that through the Condemnation that may ſpring, which never yet was found: For certainly till there be a coming through the Miniſtration of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, the Pearl is hid under the Earth, and the Earthly bears rule over it, whereby it ſtill in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage lyes, and the creature ſometimes led by a ſight of that which it doth not poſſeſs, holding the truth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101766:10"/> of God in that which is not his Righteouſneſs; for his Righteouſneſs is revealed by Faith through the power of him that takes away the ſin; and ſo it's not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in, by that mind which is out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: And this know aſſuredly, That many may ſee that which is afar off, and not feel the life of what they ſee; and ſo are many high profeſſors in the World, who change from one opinion to another, and are all yet but fruitleſs Trees, which are to be cut down and rooted up.</p>
               <p>And many there are who call him that is the Light Lord and Maſter, but to the Light are not obedient in ſelf-denial, nor taking up the daily-Croſs, which is the power of God, and crucifies unto the World; and ſo the firſt man of the World being not crucified nor put off, the new man is not received; and ſo little more is witneſſed by many who profeſs truth without the life, then was in the time of other Forms; for if the death be not known, the reſurrection of the Juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and the dead raiſed, then is all in vain: And this is not known by any but ſuch who know the Judgements of the Lord ſet up in the heart, and the Cup of Aſtoniſhment to the Adulterous ſeed which comes of the Will of the fleſh, and cannot lay down the life for the Friend.</p>
               <p>Wherefore (I ſay) Wait to know the Birth that is immortal, and feel that born up which never yet vvas raiſed in them, over vvhom the Vail yet is, that the free-Birth may be known, and the Seed whom God hath appointed the bleſſing unto, from under death redeemed; that by the powerful riſings thereof, the underſtanding may be opened with that which was before Forms were, that to it you may come which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth life unto the ſoul, and know a Saviour borne of the barren Womb, and a Deliverer brought forth in the place where he hath not been known, and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101766:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> plant to ſpring out of that ground which is yet dry, that it may be overſhadowed with the lovelineſs of its ſpreading forth, that a Way may be opened in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and the humble exalted in the Valley; and ſo come to learn of that which is yet little and low, and take heed of taking counſel of the Serpent, vvhoſe ſubtilty will ſoon lead forth from the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, neither cover your ſelves with any thing before the Righteouſneſs of God (which is perfect) be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but love that which comes from the man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, vvho comes to break the peace of all them who walk not in the everlaſting Way of Life. Let all them who are out of it, ſearch their hearts with the Light.</p>
               <p>And take heed of that which is high, forward, or ſtrong in the Will, [for vve are weak] which is not brought to the Croſs; for there is the firſt birth from the wrong grounds, which will ſpeake and act that which it lives not in; neither is able to confirm it in faithfulneſs to the death and loſs of all; for things may be true in themſelves, and that which is out of the truth may ſpeake of it, yet ſuch vain talkers cannot ſuffer to death for what they ſpeak.</p>
               <p>For that which cometh forth firſt, is ſtrong in the Earthly, and would live for ever, and have the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and would rule over the meeke thing in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and in others, having a ſecret deſire to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, being far unwilling to take a ſervants place; but certainly it is the meeke, humble, ſuffering ſeed (which in many is yet oppreſt) that is to laſt for ever, vvho through death comes into the Dominion.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſink down out of the airy Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſubtilty above the life, and firſt come to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with that vvhich is meek and lovv, if ever you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vvith it to reign in that peace and life vvhich from all that vvithout, the Vail, is hid; and in ſilence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101766:11"/> watch and be ſober to ſee him come which ſaves the ſoul, and clothes it with his own Righteouſneſs, that you be not found without a covering of the ſpirit, power, and life, among the fooliſh Virgins, for few there be that find the Way of life, and abide therein.</p>
               <p>And I knowing the terror of the Lord that will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come upon all them who dye out of his Covenant, therefore I warn all people every vvhere (as the Lord enlargeth me) to wait to feel the powerful Word of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and with the light to make diligent ſearch into the ground and foundation of all Profeſſions, Words and Actions.</p>
               <p>For the Lord God will make inquiſition for the blood of the Juſt, and reward the double-minded according to the intents of their hearts, the Gaul whereof will be rent with the povver of his Might, which will ſweep away the refuge of lyes, and confound your Divinations in the head of that knowledge above the ſeed; and a day of deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt come, Sword and Famine muſt you know, and the Earth to be removed, and your heavens ſhaken, that the poor may come to receive the glad tydings of the Goſpel, which is the povver of God; for the fat and the ſtrong is for judgement both vvithin &amp; without, &amp; they are ſtill ſent away empty; but the poor are they which are to be ſatisfied, not the rich, high, wiſe, ſtrong, mighty, prudent Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Orthodox Men, and zealous Profeſſors, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious Libertines, (as they are called) who profeſſe a Saviour to come; &amp; ſome would have a King to reign here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but they are not agreed how, nor when, nor where their King ſhall reign (whom they imagine ſhall come) but are ſound deſpiſers, and not lovers, nor faithful follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of him that is come, the glory of whoſe KINGDOM is already ſhining over the World, and is eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, Who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Who is our Head, our Law-giver and our King; and vve do not look for another; as the Drunkards of <hi>Ephraim</hi> do, vvho are drunk, but not vvith Wine, and ſtaggar at noon-day,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101766:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> and muſt be daſhed one againſt another, and broken to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as the potſherds of the Earth, vvho are looking for a King to come, and know not the King who is already come; Who is the Light to which they will not bow, though it in ſecret doth them reprove, and ſheweth us plainly of the Father, and lets them ſee their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>To it now therefore bovv and bend, for plainly the Lord God vvho is light vvill not alvvayes ſtrive by the light of his Son in your hearts; and this knovv, That as I tender the leaſt honeſt deſires that are begotten in any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the living Truth of God, yet I am to deal plainly vvith all, and clear my conſcience of all Who are covered vvith their ovvn conceivings, and in Words and Writing to vvarn all in the ſpirit of truth and meekneſs, as the Lord moveth me in faithfulneſs to declare againſt that vvhich yet in any bears rule over the Seed, vvhich by judgement muſt be overturned, and all the judgements of the Lord are true.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ye that are vvilling to come out of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions into that vvhere the fooliſh virgins cannot enter, wait in the fear of the Lord to feele his Work vvithin, vvhile the day of ſalvation laſteth, leaſt thick darkneſſe come upon you, and you be found in the night in vvhich none can vvork; and take heed of a ſecret high minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and prize your day of viſitation more then life or liberty, and take heed of that vvhich vvould contrive a vvay to ſhun the croſs, or ſtop the mouth of the vvitneſs; but let the honeſt ſimplicity come to rule in the meaſure of it, and take heed of entring in, and yeilding to temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for many vvayes hath the Serpent (vvhich is near) to beguile and deſtroy the life from man, vvhich is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, but in the continual fear, through the croſs to the Will, vvith the povver of the light vvhich is given to lead through all theſe things, into the reſt vvhich is prepared onely for them vvho are faithful to the light.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101766:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> For this have I not learned nor received from men, (the Lord God knovveth I lye not) but through the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the mighty povver of God, vvhoſe indignation I have born, in vvhoſe judgements I rejoyce for ever, and glorifie and praiſe his bleſſed Name, vvho by it my Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom confounded, and ſuffered me to be ſifted and tempted by the Enemy divers vvayes, yet preſerved my life under the ſhadovv of his Wing, that I might praiſe and ſerve him in the Land of the living, and declare his Wonders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſons of men, and let them alſo ſee vvith the light the narrovv vvay that they are to come, vvhich in ſome meaſure hath been declared, though in that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage vvhich the Wiſdom of the World may not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and call it legal, to vvhom as fooliſhneſs it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; but my voice may be knovvn to the ſpirit in priſon, vvhom my ſoul travels for in the bovvels of my Fathers love.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. S.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
